<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
         xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
   <rdf:Description>
      <dc:title>A Dictionary of Cebuano Visayan</dc:title>
      <dc:creator>John U. Wolff</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Project Gutenberg, Urbana, Illinois, USA., 2012-06-24</dc:publisher>
      <dc:date>2012-06-24</dc:date>
      <dc:rights>This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and with almost no restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms of the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or online at www.gutenberg.org. 
This eBook is produced by the Online Distributed Proofreading Team at www.pgdp.net. 
This edition of John U. Wolff’s Dictionary of Cebuano Visayan, attempts to faithfully reproduce the text of this work as originally published. Except for corrections of obvious mistakes, as listed in the colophon, no changes have been made.
Scans for this dictionary are available from Cornell University. 
This Project Gutenberg text is derived from data also made available in its master format at GitHub.
A searchable interface to the same data is available from www.bohol.ph. An off-line Android app is available from the Google Play store, for which the source code is available from BitBucket.

</dc:rights>
      <dc:subject>Cebuano language</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Dictionaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>English</dc:subject>
      <dc:description>A Dictionary of Cebuano Visayan, edited by John U Wolf and first published in 1972, is still one of the best dictionaries made for Cebuano. It was based on original research between 1966 and 1972, in which the editor and his team collected samples of actual written and spoken Cebuano to use in this dictionary. Besides providing English definitions, it provides sample sentences for many words, all taken from daily usage.</dc:description>
      <dc:identifier>pg:40074</dc:identifier>
   </rdf:Description>
</rdf:RDF>
